<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: talktext | aerenchyma]]></title>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/categories/talktext/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-26T17:23:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jackie Cohen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[what would you say?]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2011/11/07/what-would-you-say/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-07T16:10:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2011/11/07/what-would-you-say</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.igniteannarbor.com/" target="_blank">Five minutes. Twenty slides. What would you say?</a></p>

<p>I spoke at Ignite Ann Arbor on Sunday -- "Data Entry, Coffee Dripping, and Other Things as Interesting as Watching Paint Dry." You can see the video and my slides linked on my <a href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/about/">about</a> page.</p>

<p>A year ago, I was talking about that with a friend in the common room of my co-op. I wrote about that in my first grad school applications. Months later, the same friend suggested I do an Ignite talk about paint drying. He was only half joking, if that.</p>

<p>I considered the idea and I waited and on October tenth (the deadline for the call for speakers) I figured if I never pressed the button, well, I never would.</p>

<p>I did.</p>

<p>I was accepted, and really nervous, and it turned out awesome, Ignite 6. It was awesome for me because I did fine and enjoyed it as I did it. It was pretty much the opposite of painful, though that's in no small part due to practice and Emily (<a href="https://twitter.com/epuckett">@epuckett</a>)'s advice -- and because of all the people who showed up to see it, and also the people who came to see me. I'm grateful to have so many fantastic friends, people who wanted to be there, supportive people I work with; their help was incredibly valuable.</p>

<p>It's harder to prepare for those five minutes than to actually do it. It's easy to forget how many people applied for a similar reason to me and have similar amounts of public speaking experience (not tons, at the time, though it wasn't the public speaking aspect that worried me -- it was whether I would disappoint myself in my representation, because the process of paint drying, like the chemicals in coffee and data entry jobs, is seriously cool).</p>

<p>Awesome, because I know now what goes into preparing for that and it's more impressive up close, though it was impressive from further away too. Awesome, because there was stuff about food and cold (and a lot about energy) and schooling and learning and applying lessons from non-school, and there were interested people in the audience, which is a good part. "Science is cool, y'all."</p>

<p>Let it be noted, for the sake of honesty, that I spent the two weeks prior to speaking almost wishing I hadn't applied, fighting procrastination of completing my slides because of the nervousness, and then slightly freaking out about arranging what I would say (yes, in that order). "Tell me not to do it," I said, of deciding to do a presentation ever again. "Don't let me do this ever again. Stop me." A friend said, "I won't. But yeah, okay." I made a face, in part because I guessed he might be right.</p>

<p>Well, okay: He was right, as was the friend who told me to do it in the first place, and I've learnt my lesson.</p>

<p>I am more than pleased to have done this. Also -- "How'd you get to be such a geek?" -- best compliment I've ever received from someone I didn't already know.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
