<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[everything's interesting]]></title>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-11T04:10:01-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jackie Cohen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 things I learnt as default tech support]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/04/10/10-things-i-learned-as-default-tech-support/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-10T09:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/04/10/10-things-i-learned-as-default-tech-support</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Sometimes, the best system is Windows XP and Word 2000 and the mail app you hate.</p></li>
<li><p>The hardest part of unpaid tech support is sometimes learning when not to argue about (1).</p></li>
<li><p>&#8220;Being unpaid tech support&#8221; == being the youngest person in a group by 20+ years, having the most technical experience in a group re: profession or degree, or whichever turns out to be most applicable.</p></li>
<li><p>&#8220;whichever turns out to be the most applicable&#8221; in (8) is chiefly determined by your confidence in tone, if there is any question as to who&#8217;s landed the job.</p></li>
<li><p>&#8220;Why&#8221; is the easiest question to ask and the hardest one to answer.*</p></li>
<li><p>I do not like the Mac OS X mail app.</p></li>
<li><p>Even beginning to describe the differences between what you work on and what their problem is tends to be worth it approximately 15% of the time. **</p></li>
<li><p>The fact that email (and all of the cloud) is (<em>theoretically</em>) unconstrained by political boundaries is a real conceptual jump from &#8220;snail mail.&#8221; Especially if one&#8217;s professional life has been largely spent, for example, writing books on yellow notepads.</p></li>
<li><p>&#8220;I can solve this problem I&#8217;ve never seen before&#8221;, outside of work or a personal project, is often worth the frustration.***</p></li>
<li><p>You&#8217;re probably familiar with <a href="http://xkcd.com/627/">the quintessential flow chart</a> (credit Randall Monroe under a <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/">BY-NC</a> license), but there are people for whom the system this chart depends on makes sense, and there are people to whom it&#8217;s another universe. The boundary is fluid &#8211; I firmly believe this &#8211; but if you&#8217;re the resident expert (or whatever), it sure doesn&#8217;t feel that way.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><font size="-4"></p>

<p>*I have further thoughts about this, but they&#8217;re neither publicly available or all written down</p>

<p>**I made this number up.</p>

<p>*** Not always.
</font></p>

<p><font size="-4"><strong>notes on tech support background below</strong></font></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><font size="-4">
I&#8217;ve worked in desktop support &#8211; a little over two years ago now, on a hospital IT staff. I&#8217;ve also had interactions for a long time with others working in tech support roles/full-time jobs throughout most of my life. The post itself was prompted by a vacation on which I was the youngest by 45 years: let&#8217;s guess what happened, eh? I think it was destined to be at that point, whether or not I&#8217;d actually let on that I work with computers.</p>

<p>A lot of years ago, young me, and my even younger brother, accidentally changed the resolution on the computer once and, after some struggles to return the icons to their usual, unpixelated sizes, I sent a good friend of our dad&#8217;s, a computer consultant, a detailed email about what had happened and what we&#8217;d tried, asking how to fix it. He was grateful for the detail (&#8220;you wouldn&#8217;t believe how many people don&#8217;t&#8230;&#8221;), and I was grateful in return. I don&#8217;t have the email anymore, but I remember it. And the worry over tales in the hospital IT office of doctors known to have a roar specially bottled for the tech support was assuaged by the look on the face of the nurse to whom I explained the use of a laptop trackpad.</p>

<p>This is to say, oh hey sarcasm font? (it keeps me alive! :D :D) &#8211; and I really admire for the patient people who work(ed) full- or part-time in tech support longer than I have done so far. It&#8217;s a really important job in a million circumstances, and it leads to pretty interesting revelations. (This vacation? I swear I didn&#8217;t scream, just almost. But I learnt a lot.) I obviously have only my fraction of the experiences, yes. As usual, I welcome criticism and respect trying to learn new things. As with all lists of wide and silly generalizations, exceptions exist by the thousand, I know. [I&#8217;ve spent a lot (a LOT) of time on the internet.]
</font></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[instabitly]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/03/25/instabitly/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-25T00:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/03/25/instabitly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quick drive-by: <a href="https://github.com/aerenchyma/instabitly">instabitly</a>, a script I wrote recently to import saved links from <a href="http://instapaper.com">Instapaper</a> to <a href="https://bitly.com/">bit.ly</a>.</p>

<p>I did it for personal reasons &#8211; primarily because I want all this stuff stored redundantly. Obviously I haven&#8217;t solved that problem in its entirety, but there were also other reasons. Because I care about things like this. There&#8217;s a README. More, like more in the other documentation series I&#8217;ve discussed so far, will have to appear after recent projects calm down some.</p>

<p>Let me also take this opportunity to encourage you to <a href="http://www.instapaper.com/subscription">support Instapaper</a> if you can and it&#8217;s a service you like/use.</p>

<p>In my imaginary free time, I have been trying to absorb all the <a href="http://pyvideo.org/category/33/pycon-us-2013">fantastic PyCon</a> <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/pyconslides">talks</a> (I have an active imagination).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open.Michigan Analytics, the what]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-18T17:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting in January 2013, I have been a part-time software developer at the <a href="http://open.umich.edu">Open.Michigan Initiative</a>, which is housed within the Enabling Technologies office of the University of Michigan Medical School Information Services department. (I also do other things within Enabling Technologies, but for the moment and this documentation, that&#8217;s not relevant.)</p>

<p>Open.Michigan (OM) promotes open licensing and open educational resources (OER), and we publish OER on our website, which is run on the <a href="https://github.com/openmichigan/OERbit">OERbit</a> framework, which in turn is based on <a href="http://drupal.org/">Drupal</a>.</p>

<p><small>(True to our goals, all the code we produce is open source, free for use and adaptation with attribution. See licenses.)</small></p>

<p>My first project is <strong>Open.Michigan Analytics</strong> &#8211; accessing, displaying, and allowing access to analytics for the resources we publish. (Hereafter tagged as &#8221;<a href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/categories/om-analytics/">om-analytics</a>.&#8221;) With encouragement from my amazing supervisors, I am documenting the process, including decisions and missteps as well as step-by-steps of enacted processes. Below, I set out the original planning stages and goals for the project. Soon: the first decisions made, setup issues, and options I set out for proceeding.</p>

<!-- more -->


<hr />

<h4>01/22/2013:</h4>

<h3>Original plan, analytics project</h3>

<p><em>Our original outline of the project plan, in phases</em></p>

<h3><em>Phase I</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> Display (publically) specific analytics on a given course/resource page.</li>
<li><strong>Primary audience:</strong> authors of content, and U/M leadership.</li>
<li><strong>Motivation:</strong> use analytics display as way of promoting creation of open content?

<ul>
<li>Being able to show results of open content creation and publishing to content-creators.</li>
<li>&#8220;This has been viewed this many times&#8230;&#8221;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Substance:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Google Analytics:

<ul>
<li>total zip downloads #</li>
<li>most downloaded material (of materials included in a course/resource on OERbit)</li>
<li>total views of course/resource</li>
<li>date last material added (?) n.b. this info included in &#8220;date last modified&#8221; field on page</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>YouTube Analytics:

<ul>
<li>total youtube views (of videos for a given course/resource)</li>
<li>total youtube comments (#, potentially store data, depending upon TOS)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase II</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> flesh out display and available downloads</li>
<li><strong>Primary audience:</strong> same as <em>Phase I</em></li>
<li><strong>Motivation:</strong> same as above, with additonal possibility of content creators drilling deeper into analytics, personal results of content-creation, a better understanding for OM wrt which access points are used in what ways, which forms of material seem to be used most often, etc.</li>
</ul>


<p>[Below is significantly paraphrased from our original internal outline.]</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Substance:</strong>

<ul>
<li><em>Display, for a given course/resource:</em>

<ul>
<li>Social media stuff</li>
<li><a href="http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/">Deep Blue</a> downloads/views</li>
<li>Wikipedia stuff</li>
<li>number of countries accessed</li>
<li>geographic views
Downloads &#8211;</li>
<li>YouTube comments (pending TOS), demographics, site demographics</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase III</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> increased availability of and access to analytics information</li>
<li><strong>Potentially:</strong>

<ul>
<li>integrate iTunes U</li>
<li><a href="http://www.carma.umich.edu/">CARMA</a> views</li>
<li>more download options</li>
<li>further API options</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Considerations:</strong> API updates, integration of APIs, structure of personal metadata and paradata, relation to other projects, modularity, documentation forms, UI design</li>
</ul>


<p>This plan was soon substantially revised &#8211; so exciting, right? More to come; drafts in progress. (Internal documentation + development does come first.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing, testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/initial-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-18T15:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/initial-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Initial post. Content to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
