<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: teaching | j{ackie} zetta {cohen}.net]]></title>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/categories/teaching/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-11T19:14:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jackie Cohen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[we can go the distance]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2015/05/01/go-the-distance/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-01T11:59:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2015/05/01/go-the-distance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Years ago, I wrote <a href="http://jczetta.net/blog/2012/05/02/highlight-of-the-job/">this</a>.</p>

<p>I moved away, thinking I'd spent my last autumn as a student in Michigan, and wished those who came after me the best. I wrote in that thing that I wished I could do it again, but I was moving away, hoping there'd be something similar somewhere else. I was so sorry that I couldn't see the repeat, though.</p>

<p>The work I did for the next couple years was informed over and over again by what I did and how I felt that semester, newly graduated, teaching people things. What I didn't realize 100% at the time was that the necessity of being a voice of authority, and even more, a voice of calm when learning frustrating things, taught me -- yeah, yeah -- how to be the teacher and the person I wanted to be. Remember when you sat down and built that app for them? You can do it again. I can think of few things as helpful and as useful.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>A year and a half ago, again a student in Michigan (that's another story) I saw a posting for a GSI (Graduate Student Instructor) position, the same professor as the professor for that class I refer to above. SI 106: Introductory Programming, economics of open source.</p>

<p>He hired me.</p>

<p>This week I wrapped up what for now is my last semester of three in a row teaching. With this week comes the end of my graduate school career (for now, probably forever), and also, undoubtedly, the end of one of the <em>best</em> jobs. I have been delighted to be a part of this in every way.</p>

<p>In 2012 I waxed nostalgic quickly, sappy as anything, wondering if my career path had been changed -- yeah, it had been. I guess I probably knew that then.</p>

<p>The three semesters of Graduate Student Instruction (GSI is what U-M calls graduate student TAs, essentially) that that IA job basically led to have been some of the best of my life to this point. The job teaching students new to, and long familiar with, college has taught me so much about leadership and mentorship, team building and explanations and pedagogy. About people. About frustration and programming and Python and operatingn systems and the Internet, about systematic thinking and management and procrastination and friendship and creativity and writing. But seriously; all of the above. This has been a light every day, an anchor, a reminder about pretty much all the things, even the non-obvious things, that I love about my life. Pretty much the best job I can imagine for the time, even if not forever. (I'm not that into "forever.") It has been immensely frustrating and tiring and stressful, and worth every moment of twelve-hour grading sessions and mornings that felt much too early and falling asleep on windowsills. Worth it, for every smile on someone's face when they understand something new, every acknowledging nod, every brave question as students come to my office hours and raise their hands in my section and tell me, and people around them, that there's something they don't know, but they want to know, and everything I've learned about and laughed about with the people working alongside me, who have been reliably incredible.</p>

<p>That never gets less amazing. I've in some capacity or other been a teacher for, now, almost 300 students and I remember most of them (maybe all? The uncertainty is because I haven't gone through to prove it and I'm not sure I have the access to), and every one of them has taught me something, probably, even the people I barely met in person (in someone else's section, non-attending engineers taking an easy class...). It sounds exaggerated, ridiculous, but I'm not really sure that it is. There are so many flavors of worry and bravery, so many different flashes of younger versions of me I see in other people and attitudes toward a class, or the world, that I'm not sure I understand. Every week I have to remember, and am thrilled to remember: I probably don't know your life, or what it's like, and it is not my job to make those judgments. It is my job to convey information and try to make it accessible and clear. It is my job to be your advocate in this space, and that is enough to quell frustration and most exhaustion both.</p>

<p>It is so much to be the person things are told to. I remember professors' and GSIs' reactions to end-of-semester panic and assignment-turn-ins more than many things that blurred together in my four years of college as a student, and to be the source of that is incredible to me. I see people do this irresponsibly. I promise, and am proud to be able to promise, that I will do my best to never do that, even if I am not a student in a formal school environment anymore. I will not make fun of you such that it's mean. You are forced to trust us teachers with things -- that's a big deal, and I respect that, so much. And on this side of the metaphorical curtain, to have gotten to share all this with other people sharing this role, or set of roles, with me, and talk about it to make us all better at it -- holy crap, basically.</p>

<p>I sat down in office hours this past semester and told the story of coming home from my first programming class mid-semester, feeling entirely useless. "I can't do this, I think," they tell me. I said, you know what? I'm getting hired as a software engineer. And I came from that. I see you. You can do this, too, if you want to, and we are here to help. It was true. I was right. I love being right! (Sometimes.)</p>

<p>I walk down the halls of my department building. Everyone in that class I wrote about in 2012 who was not a freshman at the time, or who was graduating early, is already done with college. One of those kids is a classmate of my fellow GSI in Winter 2014; she'll graduate from grad school this week just like me (with less time off between, presumably), and I'm sure she's not the only one. One of the freshmen, to whom I obliquely referred in that post three years ago, stops me in the hall more than once. "Hey, Jackie! How's it going?" A year ago, he tells me he's building rails apps. Now he's selling his stuff so he can leave town. I clap very loudly for him at graduation.</p>

<p>I got to work with former students. They teach me more about how to look at the world and new ways of thinking about grade organization and understanding concepts and music and just being a person.</p>

<p>This job and what I love about it led me to my next one.</p>

<p>It's like <a href="http://xkcd.com/353/">flying</a>. The Python helps, for sure, but it's not everything.</p>

<p>I am so proud of being part of communities which try to be iteratively better. Consistently more welcoming. The <a href="http://recurse.com/about">Recurse Center</a> is one. <a href="http://commoncycle.org/">Common Cycle</a> is another, a place where it's become clear I am one instigator of change but so far from the only one, a place where I am listened to without shouting (more on this another time, probably elsewhere), a place that helps people in ways I care about. A place that is about learning and teaching as totally integrated processes. I am so proud of that. This class has been another, and I look forward to all of them I'm already part of and will keep stepping into in the future. What can we do better? What do we know? Would this be interesting? Who does this serve? Why, why, why, and also how? This stuff is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2aqpF-MwyUs">always sappy</a>, I know, but I have to say I don't care -- at least, I don't mind. There aren't a lot of things I am willing to speak publically about like this, but this matters too much.</p>

<p>"I guess I'll see," I said. I was wrong about not getting to iterate on my experience. I got to see! How cool is that!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[highlight of the job]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2012/05/02/highlight-of-the-job/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T14:15:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2012/05/02/highlight-of-the-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On May first, I reached the end of Michigan's 2012 Winter semester, and with it the end of one of the best jobs. A student called the deadline for the final projects the "end of an era" -- that's what it felt like to us (the staff), too. ("It feels like we're doing twenty projects!")</p>

<p>Except that it's more thrilling to watch people work together and seriously, rapidly and usefully learn stuff, and help each other -- better to watch forty-some eureka moments than only have a few yourself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I've been very lucky jobwise, this school year, overall. But the off-chance I got to IA for an intro programming class has lit up my life, in the worst, best, and cheesiest sense of the words. (I know, I make me feel ill, too.) Nothing, except living in a co-op, has taught me more about <i>people</i> and dealing with and reacting to others responsibly; in no job I've ever had, including 'being a full-time student', have I ever come home feeling like I did as many worthwhile things with my day (though certainly there are others where finishing weeks, or projects, has left me feeling as accomplished).</p>

<p>But I've rarely been as amazed as I often was in that lecture hall. I feel like I got to know more than fifty people this past semester, and when they left the exam, I was glad for them all, and my co-IA (who was brilliant) and I were, if anything, underestimating when we told them how proud we were and how much luck we wished for them in the future. I've never seen students leave an exam with so much glee and pride, and I've never been so sorry to see quite that many people go. (I didn't get along with <i>that</i> many people in my high school class... that's been a while.)</p>

<p>I've known for years that teaching someone else is one of the best ways to learn something thoroughly, but I didn't know the extent to which it would change how I thought about learning, and how I thought about myself. My students have taught me good lessons over and over again. Those who struggled with concepts and kept coming back, those who leaned over to help others without giving them the answers. "Let's break it down." Those who played music as office hours before the final crept later and later, and laughed when I danced (just a little). "Even the GSIs are getting into it!" Well, yeah -- we want to have fun too. (GSIs we weren't, but for all intents and purposes. It was a position I'm not used to being in, but I enjoyed it.)</p>

<p>I felt heading into the job that in terms of programming, a strength of mine was explaining programming concepts, because I struggled at first and then crested the -- what? the hill of difficulty? and have loved programming and building things with code ever since, but in my upper-level classes, I recognized my students' struggle on a new level and I sympathized, and I think that helped. Time-depth-wise, I was closer to their level than the rest of the staff team, by quite a lot, and though that made me nervous at the get-go, it turned out to be really valuable. I'm endlessly glad I was not the only staff member, but I work well in a team anyway (and I had an <i>awesome</i> co-IA). It is difficult to remember what it's like <i>not</i> to know stuff (e.g. what it means to store a Python dictionary in a variable, what a for-loop does), but I found the reach backwards easier and easier as I went on. As I told the professor for whom I worked, I found myself using more than anything else things I'd learnt while playing around on my own, and things I'd learnt in the class itself, more than I used knowledge from subsequent classes.</p>

<p>Every meaningful "thank you" was ridiculously valuable to me. Every moment of sudden understanding. The look on one girl's face as she got a web app working: "This is the best thing I've ever seen in my whole life; I'm so happy!" A guy's grin as he said "Oh! We're extracting information from the internet!" The genial frustration ("I'm back to make your life miserable, Jackie!" / "Never. What's up?"). The glee I came to expect as I whirled on a heel to say "YES! Exactly! So what type will this be?"</p>

<p>I wanted to make a pun about dynamism and Python being dynamically typed here, but instead I'll say that students gave me and my co-IA thank you cards they signed, and nominated us for awards that we weren't quite eligible for (not being grad students), so the school we worked for invented a new award for us -- but the students' high-fives and compliments to each other because they understood what the others were doing with APIs and Oauth tokens were the best part. "Amazing work," they started saying to each other -- and to <i>us</i> -- and I couldn't agree more. It isn't that there were no painful or frustrating parts -- holy, were there ever -- but that all of them were worth it, and I learnt a lot about how I'd deal with them if that were on me. Maybe someday. I'm only sorry I can't IA this class again.</p>

<p>Sappy as hell, OK. Who knows, that might've changed my career path. I guess I'll see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[and some killer awesome students, too]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2012/03/06/and-some-killer-awesome-students/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T16:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2012/03/06/and-some-killer-awesome-students</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A brief interlude, relating to teaching programming. My co-IA and I subbed for lecture today; the professor we work for is at a conference in another state.</p>

<p>The class has a facebook group for posting tips and asking each other questions. Halfway through class (I found this out afterward), this appears on the group, and by half an hour after the class is over, it looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://jaclynzetta.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/screen-shot-2012-03-06-at-4-17-18-pm.png" alt="image of a facebook post that says We have some killer GSIs for this class. 21 people like this, 5 comments." /></p>

<p>What a great job.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
