<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: maps | everything's interesting]]></title>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/categories/maps/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-21T15:55:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jackie Cohen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Globes and maps]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/07/25/globes-and-maps/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T17:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/07/25/globes-and-maps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://bit.ly/18Akcfu">Writes Bonnie Bogle of MapBox</a>,  "The diversity of our team has made our team stronger, our tools better, and our approaches smarter and more innovative."</p>

<p>The aim I see here is really great. This is what I'd like to see more of.</p>

<p>When industries, platforms, and organizations I care about acknowledge not just that they care about diversity, but that they can explain why they care and what they want to do, that they're serious for real reasons, I am pretty likely to talk about them positively, and excitedly, and often, to want to and try to use their products or services. I don't think I'm alone there.</p>

<p>I'm glad to see this for many reasons, obviously. But maps affect nearly everyone in some way or another. Maps have effects on everyone and how people deal with others. How they travel. What they think of places they frequent and places they've never been. I don't know this for sure, but I know it for me, and I see evidence of it everywhere. Maps help people form opinions on and gain knowledge about the public transit systems available (and unavailable!) to them. From maps arise issues of accessibility on multiple axes, a lot of frustration, metric tons of joy. (I love maps.) They help and hurt, but mostly, and certainly ideally, I believe they can and should and do help, and I think the world is moving closer, closer, to wholly positive maps all the time.</p>

<p>There's always a long way to go but maps help me figure that out.</p>

<p>So for now, yeah: this made me happy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
