<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open.michigan | aerenchyma]]></title>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/categories/open-michigan/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-16T14:32:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jackie Cohen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open.Michigan Analytics, the what]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-18T17:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.io/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting in January 2013, I have been a software developer at the <a href="http://open.umich.edu">Open.Michigan Initiative</a>, which is housed within the University of Michigan Medical School. Open.Michigan (OM) promotes open licensing and open educational resources (OER), and we publish OER on our website, which is run on the <a href="https://github.com/openmichigan/OERbit">OERbit</a> framework, which in turn is based on <a href="http://drupal.org/">Drupal</a>.</p>

<p><small>(True to our goals, all the code we produce is open source, free for use and adaptation with attribution. See licenses.)</small></p>

<p>My first project is Open.Michigan Analytics -- accessing, displaying, and allowing access to analytics for the resources we publish. In twelve words or fewer. Hah. I am documenting the process, including decisions and missteps as well as step-by-steps of enacted processes, especially because this includes my progress learning Drupal (I am flexible with languages, but I have most experience developing in Python, and I had never worked even semi-professionally in PHP before this project), and adaptations and contributions to a fairly new open source project, examples of which are good to have. Also, if anyone picks this up inside or outside our office, I'd like to have documentation of the development (and not just its use) around.</p>

<p>Below, I set out the original planning stages and goals for the project. Soon: the first decisions made, setup issues, and options I set out for proceeding.</p>

<!-- more -->


<hr />

<h4>01/22/2013:</h4>

<h3>Original plan, analytics project</h3>

<p><em>Our original outline of the project plan, in phases</em></p>

<h3><em>Phase I</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> Display (publically) specific analytics on a given course/resource page.</li>
<li><strong>Primary audience:</strong> authors of content, and U/M leadership.</li>
<li><strong>Motivation:</strong> use analytics display as way of promoting creation of open content?

<ul>
<li>Being able to show results of open content creation and publishing to content-creators.</li>
<li>"This has been viewed this many times..."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Substance:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Google Analytics:

<ul>
<li>total zip downloads #</li>
<li>most downloaded material (of materials included in a course/resource on OERbit)</li>
<li>total views of course/resource</li>
<li>date last material added (?) n.b. this info included in "date last modified" field on page</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>YouTube Analytics:

<ul>
<li>total youtube views (of videos for a given course/resource)</li>
<li>total youtube comments (#, potentially store data, depending upon TOS)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase II</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> flesh out display and available downloads</li>
<li><strong>Primary audience:</strong> same as <em>Phase I</em></li>
<li><strong>Motivation:</strong> same as above, with additonal possibility of content creators drilling deeper into analytics, personal results of content-creation, a better understanding for OM wrt which access points are used in what ways, which forms of material seem to be used most often, etc.</li>
</ul>


<p>[Below is significantly paraphrased from our original internal outline.]</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Substance:</strong>

<ul>
<li><em>Display, for a given course/resource:</em>

<ul>
<li>Social media stuff</li>
<li><a href="http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/">Deep Blue</a> downloads/views</li>
<li>Wikipedia stuff</li>
<li>number of countries accessed</li>
<li>geographic views</li>
<li>Downloads -- YouTube comments (pending TOS), demographics, site demographics</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase III</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> increased availability of and access to analytics information</li>
<li><strong>Potentially:</strong>

<ul>
<li>integrate iTunes U</li>
<li><a href="http://www.carma.umich.edu/">CARMA</a> views</li>
<li>more download options</li>
<li>further API options</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Considerations:</strong> API updates, integration of APIs, structure of personal metadata and paradata, relation to other projects, modularity, documentation forms, UI design</li>
</ul>


<p>This plan was soon substantially revised -- so exciting, right? More to come; drafts in progress. (Internal documentation + development does come first.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
