<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open.michigan | everything's interesting]]></title>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/categories/open-michigan/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-21T15:03:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jackie Cohen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open.Michigan Analytics, the how (part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/20/open-dot-michigan-analytics/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-20T10:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/20/open-dot-michigan-analytics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so I wanted <a href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics/">analytics</a>. That meant I needed to access and manipulate data, naturally. The phases laid out in the intial plan in that previous, linked, post were discussed during a meeting to kick off the project, the first day I came back to the office (I worked at a different job at Open.Michigan for nine months 2011 - 2012).</p>

<p>After the whats and the whys came the hows, and my job. What is the appropriate technical architecture for this task? (Spoiler: no Answers* here)</p>

<!--more-->


<h3><em>Facts:</em></h3>

<ul>
<li>OERbit/we run Drupal 6.x</li>
<li>Our servers shouldn't take too much <em>more</em> load</li>
<li>We want to run fully open-source software and free software</li>
<li>MySQL is our db</li>
<li>Sustainability of and access to the analytics system matters</li>
<li>The base technical architecture for OERbit isn't changing (at least, definitely not changing for this small piece)</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Resources:</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/aerenchyma/5007683">Python</a> <a href="https://gist.github.com/aerenchyma/5007667">scripts</a> that were written to gather Google Analytics and Youtube Analytics data (for the <a href="https://open.umich.edu/blog/2013/02/20/championing-data-analysis-at-the-sophomore-a2datadive/">DataDive</a>)</li>
<li><a href="http://blog.amazeelabs.com/en/create-ultimate-google-analytics-dashboard-drupal-part-1">documentation</a> of similar(?) analytics projects on Drupal</li>
<li>Drupal plugins galore?</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Options/considerations:</em></h3>

<ul>
<li>Is there a Drupal plugin (or multiple) that suits our needs?</li>
<li>Can we customize a Drupal plugin to suit our needs? Or write a new one?</li>
<li>Should we write custom code? (Probably JavaScript)</li>
<li>Are there other options we're not thinking about?</li>
<li>What useful (openly licensed) code is available? (Reuse, reuse, reuse)</li>
</ul>


<p>And, in my mind: how can I use my skillset to work on this project most efficiently? At the start, I'd done very little programming in PHP, but was comfortable with Python and Ruby and reasonably comfortable with JavaScript. PHP is "like nothing else" and "exactly like all the other scripting languages, except with its own special things" (anonymity protected..). As I write, I'm still muddling around in the PHP world, hopefully to some success.</p>

<p>With an overarching goal of accessing the appropriate information and manipulating it, I had two immediate goals:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install a local instance of the OERbit software on my computer, for development</li>
<li>Edit the extant Python scripts such that they got us the information we wanted, because they were existing resources</li>
</ol>


<p>(1) proved to be much more difficult than any of us expected, but it was a learning process... which involved the office buying <a href="http://www.mamp.info/en/index.html">MAMP</a> Pro and me installing the university-bought-license of the software on a loaner laptop, clean of my local db issues -- at which point, with a great deal of help from the primary developers of OERbit, my life became much easier (the 2007 Macbook Pro is a pretty nice machine! If heavy <code>/spoiltbyAir</code>).</p>

<p>Documentation of this process (the way it should go) should appear on our wiki in future; documentation of the issues I have should appear internally (hopefully no one else will have to deal with exactly that. Be careful installing MySQL <s>for funsies</s>, all).</p>

<p>(2) was fun. More to come.</p>

<p>*<small>Yes, the capital 'A' is on purpose</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open.Michigan Analytics, the what]]></title>
    <link href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-18T17:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/2013/02/18/open-dot-michigan-analytics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting in January 2013, I have been a part-time software developer at the <a href="http://open.umich.edu">Open.Michigan Initiative</a>, which is housed within the Enabling Technologies office of the University of Michigan Medical School Information Services department. (I also do other things within Enabling Technologies, but for the moment and this documentation, that's not relevant.)</p>

<p>Open.Michigan (OM) promotes open licensing and open educational resources (OER), and we publish OER on our website, which is run on the <a href="https://github.com/openmichigan/OERbit">OERbit</a> framework, which in turn is based on <a href="http://drupal.org/">Drupal</a>.</p>

<p><small>(True to our goals and our message(s), all the code we produce is open source, free for use and adaptation with attribution. See licenses.)</small></p>

<p>My first project is <strong>Open.Michigan Analytics</strong> -- accessing, displaying, and allowing access to analytics for the resources we publish. (Hereafter tagged as "<a href="http://aerenchyma.github.com/blog/categories/om-analytics/">om-analytics</a>.") With encouragement from my amazing supervisors, I am documenting the process, including decisions and missteps as well as step-by-steps of enacted processes. Below, I set out the original and revised planning stages, and goals for the project. Soon: the first decisions made, setup issues, and options I set out for proceeding.</p>

<!-- more -->


<hr />

<h4>01/22/2013:</h4>

<h3>Original plan, analytics project</h3>

<p><em>Our original outline of the project plan, in phases</em></p>

<h3><em>Phase I</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> Display (publically) specific analytics on a given course/resource page.</li>
<li><strong>Primary audience:</strong> authors of content, and U/M leadership.</li>
<li><strong>Motivation:</strong> use analytics display as way of promoting creation of open content?

<ul>
<li>Being able to show results of open content creation and publishing to content-creators.</li>
<li>"This has been viewed this many times..."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Substance:</strong>

<ul>
<li>Google Analytics:

<ul>
<li>total zip downloads #</li>
<li>most downloaded material (of materials included in a course/resource on OERbit)</li>
<li>total views of course/resource</li>
<li>date last material added (?) n.b. this info included in "date last modified" field on page</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>YouTube Analytics:

<ul>
<li>total youtube views (of videos for a given course/resource)</li>
<li>total youtube comments (#, potentially store data, depending upon TOS)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase II</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> flesh out display and available downloads</li>
<li><strong>Primary audience:</strong> same as <em>Phase I</em></li>
<li><strong>Motivation:</strong> same as above, with additonal possibility of content creators drilling deeper into analytics, personal results of content-creation, a better understanding for OM wrt which access points are used in what ways, which forms of material seem to be used most often, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Substance:</strong>

<ul>
<li><em>Display, for a given course/resource:</em>

<ul>
<li>Facebook Likes</li>
<li>Tweets</li>
<li><a href="http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/">Deep Blue</a> downloads/views</li>
<li>Wikipedia views</li>
<li>number of countries accessed (Google Analytics/YouTube)</li>
<li>views within (state of?) Michigan, vs. elsewhere</li>
<li>potentially a map of views?
  (can we create a map from a web interface?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><em>Available for download:</em>

<ul>
<li>YouTube comments (pending TOS check)</li>
<li>YouTube demographics (from YT analytics)</li>
<li>Open.Michigan (course/resource landing page? overall?) demographics</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase III</em></h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goal:</strong> increased availability of and access to analytics information</li>
<li><strong>Potentially:</strong>

<ul>
<li>integrate iTunes U</li>
<li><a href="http://www.carma.umich.edu/">CARMA</a> views</li>
<li>more download options</li>
<li>?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h4>~02/01/2013:</h4>

<h3>Revised plan, analytics project</h3>

<p><em>Restructured plan, due to process exploration (explanation to come)</em></p>

<p><strong>Overall Goal:</strong> To be certain I can access and manipulate the information we're interested in, and then figure out what is the best way (for us) to do so</p>

<h3><em>Phase I</em></h3>

<h4>(i) <strong>Access and publically display, on course/resource landing pages:</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li>Total course/resource views (from Google Analytics (G.A.) data)</li>
<li>Total zip downloads of materials for a given course/resource (from G.A. data)</li>
<li>Most individually downloaded material/file for a given course/resource (from G.A. data)</li>
<li>(potentially) ratio of materials views : zip downloads</li>
</ul>


<h4>(ii) <strong>Access and publically display, similarly:</strong></h4>

<ul>
<li>Total YouTube views for videos belonging to given course/resource</li>
<li>Total YouTube comments (number) for videos belonging to given course/resource</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase II</em></h3>

<ul>
<li>Deepen access to analytics</li>
<li>Consider chart/graph displays</li>
<li>Make data available for download, pending TOS checks</li>
<li>Design UI</li>
</ul>


<h3><em>Phase III</em></h3>

<ul>
<li>dependent upon previous phases</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
